So remember that we start with the top of the דף daf
with the משנה. Mishnah. And here we go, we're continuing to do
special cases in שומרים. shomrim. All right, so המפקיד מעות אצל חברו.
HaMafkid ma'ot etzel chaveiro. So the last whole discussion was about when
can you sort of sell off an object because you are afraid
that it's going to get destroyed and then the next question was
really a focus on the הלכה halacha about שליחות יד shlichus yad
or actually, not clear what was going on in the משנה, Mishnah,
but taking some use of that object for your own purpose and
then when are you able to consider it returned so that your
special responsibility ends and then you're back to your normal status of
a שומר. shomer. Again, that was strange because if it was talking
about שליחות יד shlichus yad which the גמרא Gemara developed, it didn't
directly elaborate or expound on the category of שליחות יד. shlichus yad.
We'll get to that a little bit later. But now we are
going to turn to finally something which one might say is the
more basic discussion, the most basic discussion really is, there are the
following four categories: שומר חנם, shomer chinam, שומר שכר, shomer sachar, שואל,
sho'el, and a שוכר, socher, and here's their different levels of responsibility.
So that we're going to have to wait about another four פרקים.
perakim. Sorry. So anyway, but at least here we finally at the
end of this פרק perek after all these special cases, we do
have somewhat of a discussion about the level of care that is
required at least for a very specific object, for money. So let's
take a look. המפקיד מעות אצל חברו, HaMafkid ma'ot etzel chaveiro, somebody
entrusts money to his friend to watch for him. צרן והפשילן לאחוריו,
Tzaran v'hifshilan l'achorav,
if he bundled them up and had them put them behind his
back, so let' say in his pocket, back pocket, on his backpack.
או שמסרם לבנו ולבתו הקטנים, O shemasram livno ulevito haktanim, or he
gave it to his children to watch, son or daughter, minors. Minors.
Minors,
thank you. ונעל בפניהם שלא כראוי, V'na'al bifneihem shelo karauy, and locked
them in the house but not in a protected way, so that
they could possibly they could get out. שבכל אלו חייב, Shebechol elu
chayav, in that case, חייב, chayav, and something happened to them in
all those cases, whether it's putting the money behind you in your
knapsack, giving it to your kids who are minors, you're חייב. chayav.
שלא שמר כדרך השומרים, Shelo shamar k'derech hashomrim, because he didn't watch
it the normal standard that שומרים shomrim do. ואם שמר כדרך השומרים
פטור, V'im shamar k'derech hashomrim patur, but if he did it the
normal standard, פטור, patur, you're exempt, which is like so much begs
the question, right? What's the normal standard? Who defines it? Is there
different standards for שומר חנם shomer chinam or for שומר שכר? shomer
sachar? Right? So is it really completely contextual? So there's no, it's
all based on what the norms are of the society. So there's
so much here that needs to be defined. But what the גמרא
Gemara is going to hone in on is at least the first
case about putting your money in your knapsack seems to be a
very high level of care, so what else would have been a
reasonable thing to demand? Well, okay, yeah.
Is it obvious that this is שומר חנם? shomer chinam?
It is not at all obvious. Now you could say that... Yeah,
it's not at all obvious who we're talking about. Well, certainly not
a שואל, sho'el, where המפקיד, HaMafkid, המפקיד HaMafkid is either שומר חנם
shomer chinam or שומר שכר. shomer sachar. But normally I think that
the סתם מפקיד stam mafkid means without any other arrangement, so it's
just שומר חנם. shomer chinam. Okay, and certainly that's the, but you're
right, it is not clear whether a normal case about שומר shomer
is a שומר חנם shomer chinam or a שומר שכר. shomer sachar.
Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. בשלמא כולהו שלא
שמר כדרך השומרים, Bishlama kulehu shelo shamar k'derech hashomrim, I get why
giving it to your kids or the other case ונעל בפניהם שלא
כראוי. v'na'al bifneihem shelo karauy. Now the question is, are those two
cases by the way, giving it to your kids and you didn't
lock the door in of your house in front of your kids
appropriately, right? Are those two cases? One is if you give it
to your kid, that's
irresponsible as opposed to giving it to your adult children. And the
other is you walked out of the house and you didn't lock
the door well. That's probably the easier way to read it, especially
the גמרא Gemara says כולהו, kulehu, all the cases, right? And according
to that, what? But...
It's only what's the בפניהם? bifneihem?
No. בפניהם bifneihem is in front of the מעות. ma'ot. Anyway, but
the point is, so that's probably the better way of reading it,
and the גמרא Gemara here does say בשלמא כולהו, bishlama kulehu, all
the cases other than the first. And in that way of reading
it there are three cases in the משנה. Mishnah. But a previous
רש"י Rashi read that ונעל בפניהם v'na'al bifneihem means lock the door
in front of your kids. Anyway, it's try the other cases in
the משנה, Mishnah, we get it. There was a problem. שלא שמר
כדרך השומרים. Shelo shamar k'derech hashomrim. You had your minor kids watching,
that wasn't responsible. You didn't lock the door well, that wasn't responsible.
אלא צרן והפשילן לאחוריו, Ela tzaran v'hifshilan l'achorav, but if you put
them in a bundle and put it behind your back, like putting
in your knapsack, מאי הוה ליה למעבד? mai hava leh l'me'avad? What
should you have done? So אמר רבא אמר רב יצחק אמר קרא,
Amar Rava amar Rav Yitzchak amar kra, the verse says וצרת הכסף
בידך. v'tzarta hakesef b'yadecha. This is about מעשר שני. Ma'aser Sheni. You
redeem the
money, you redeem the מעשר ma'aser on the money and you bring
the money to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. And it says you should bind it
in your hand. So בידך, b'yadecha, אף על פי שצרורין, af al
pi shetzrurin, even if they're bound up and in a package, בידך,
b'yadecha, hold it in your hand. Okay, that for when it comes
to money, you have to really, you know. Make sure you're constantly
on top of it. I guess it's a big attraction for thieves.
Maybe it's a lot of value for a small, you know, in
a small package, so it's easy to lose. So you have to
be really super careful, you know, super careful about it.
Only in your hand.
Yes, it does.
Well, well, what does it really mean?
I mean, well, yeah, you have to keep it in front of
you. I don't know, keep it in your front pocket, maybe. Put
it in your front pocket, don't put it in your back pocket.
I want to remind you that רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak is the
one who said back in the second פרק, perek, back, it's thank
you, back in the second פרק perek of בבא מציעא Bava Metzia
that when the גמרא Gemara question was what if somebody dropped some
money, how can we assume יאוש, yiush, how can we assume that
they know that they dropped it? And רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak was
the one who said אדם עשוי למשמש בכיסו בכל שעה. Adam asuy
lemashmesh b'kiso b'chol sha'a. רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak said a person is
always checking their pockets to make sure the money is still there.
So it was a little bit of a קשיא kasha at the
time we thought it was descriptive, and we could question is that
really true? I mean, different people are different ways. But here one
wonders whether there is also a prescriptive, you know, element to it,
that רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak is basically saying, you know, money loses,
gets lost easily and therefore, you know, you're supposed to be, if
you have it in your pocket or whatever, so he'd like to
think that everybody is regularly checking because that's the only responsible thing
to do. So it is interesting, those two רב יצחק. Rav Yitzchaks.
And here רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak says anything that's not literally in
your hand or maybe at least in your front pocket is not
considered being fully responsible. ואמר רב יצחק, V'amar Rav Yitzchak, and now
we're going to do a little bit of an aggadic digression for
a little bit. ואמר רב יצחק, V'amar Rav Yitzchak, לעולם יהא כספו
של אדם מצוי בידו. l'olam yehei kaspah shel adam matzui b'yado. You
should always have, you know, available cash. This is מצוי. matzui. This
is not how to protect it. This is like if you have
a nice business opportunity, you know, you should always have a certain
amount of cash readily available. I guess they go hand in hand.
If you want to have cash readily available, and I not mean
that anyway, but anyway if you're supposed to have cash readily available,
you have to be taking extra care about how you're going to
watch it, right? If you always have only five dollars in your
wallet, you don't have to be super careful whether your wallet's in
your front pocket or your back pocket. But if you always should
be walking around with a few hundred dollars because you never know
what opportunity will present itself, you better make sure you're being better
about where you're putting your money. Okay, anyway, he says לעולם יהא
כספו של אדם מצוי בידו, l'olam yehei kaspah shel adam matzui b'yado,
you should always have money available, שנאמר וצרת הכסף בידך. shene'emar v'tzarta
hakesef b'yadecha.
It should be in your hand, it should always be available. You
never know what opportunity will present itself. ואמר רב יצחק, V'amar Rav
Yitzchak,
and now we're going to go to some investing advice, our portfolio
advice. You should have a diversified portfolio. לעולם ישליש אדם את מעותיו.
L'olam yashlish adam et ma'otav. You should diversify your money, you know,
in three different areas: שליש בקרקע, shlish b'karka, a third in land,
in real estate. Okay, that retains its value and
over time will go up in value and will also can't be
stolen or lost.
ושליש בפרקמטיא, ushlish b'prakmatia, a third in like commerce, business, right? You
know, sort of like buying and selling, which is maybe a higher
risk and higher return investment. Okay. ושליש תחת ידו, v'shlish tachat yado,
and a third in available funds, right? A third in cash, okay,
liquid assets. Have a certain money market. All right. So ואמר רב
יצחק, v'amar Rav Yitzchak, and רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak said, רב יצחק
Rav Yitzchak had a lot of sayings about money. אין הברכה מצויה
אלא בדבר
הסמוי מן העין. Ein habracha metzuya ela b'davar hasamui min ha'ayin. The
blessing increases found if it's hidden from the eye. If you're constantly
counting
exactly how your investment did today and yesterday and the day after
and keeping exact tracks of the amount of money, it's not going
to be blessed. Now this could be a metaphysical thing, you know,
that
you want like a miracle to happen or whatever you can't be
looking at the time. It could also be an idea that, I
mean, if you see oh it's exactly this much, if I don't
know how much then it winds up being a lot more than
I expected, whatever. You know, I'm giving God sort of the opportunity
to operate the miracles without it being a נס גלוי. nes galuy.
The other possibility
is the מהרש"א Maharsha talks about is about like the עין הרע.
ayin hara. If everything is sort of known and counted or whatever,
then other people look at it zealously and then that has some
impact on it. And psychologically, of course, this makes sense, you know,
if you don't check your, you know, your investments for a while
and then after three months you open it up and say, "Whoa,
I made a lot of money!" Right? But if you're checking it
every single day, I mean, assuming you did make money, but if
you're checking it every single day, then it doesn't feel like you're
making a lot of money because you're keeping such close track. Anyway.
What was that thing back a while back and they said you
should check once a
day, remember something?
Well, that's checking once a day about like surveying your field to
keeping on top of your workers. That's a little different than like
counting the number. I mean, the idea about counting something because of
either עין הרע ayin hara or because it like limits it, like
we have the whole thing about against counting people, right? You know,
it's obviously somewhat similar. The idea that the fish, you know, it
says כי טוב ki tov twice on, you know, on whatever on
Tuesday because, you know, of the right? Because of like the fish
and the fish are hidden from the eye and whatever. So, no,
not the fish, excuse me, not the fish. That's a different thing.
What's the thing with the fish?
וידגו לרוב בקרב הארץ.
v'yidgu larov
b'kerev ha'aretz. Right, no, yeah, the fish, what?
Yeah, the fish were the fifth day. No, there's something else about
the כי טוב ki tov and whatever.
Anyway.
All right. All right. Right. All right guys. I'm going to have
to kick you guys out if you keep on talking. All right.
All right, so okay. שנאמר יצו ה' איתך את הברכה באסמיך. Shenemar
yetzav Hashem itcha et haberacha be'asamecha. God will give you the blessing
in your gathering in. So דרשיה drashia as באסמיך be'asamecha in סמוי,
samui, hidden. תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, Tana devei Rabbi Yishmael, אין הברכה
מצויה אלא בדבר שאין העין שולטת בו. Ein haberacha metzuya ela bedavar
she'ein ha'ayin sholetet bo. Only on something the eye doesn't have mastery
over, which is pretty much saying the same thing, except this is
Rabbi Yishmael, not Rabbi Yitzchak. שנאמר יצו ה' איתך את הברכה באסמיך.
Shenemar yetzav Hashem itcha et haberacha be'asamecha. So Rashi says here the
דרשה drasha is not באסמיך be'asamecha of סמוי samui hidden, but like
באסמיך, be'asamecha, I don't know if you look at Rashi, I didn't
really get it. Rashi says where's Rashi? באסמיך דרש ליה לשון דבר
הנאכל? Be'asamecha darash leh lashon davar hane'echal? No. שאין העין שולטת בו
שנאמר באסמיך לשון גנזים, She'ein ha'ayin sholetet bo shenemar be'asamecha lashon genazim,
like the stuff that's in your treasure house. So I don't know
why that's עין שולטת בו. ayin sholetet bo. I guess it means
maybe it's not left open for everybody to look at. So the
question is is there really, you know, it's something that's stored away.
So the second point might more be the idea of protecting it
against an עין הרע. ayin hara. The eye doesn't have mastery over
it, the eye is the evil eye as opposed to the second
idea which is just that if it's hidden, you allow the blessing
a place to you know, increase because you're not tracking it. Yes.
And your ברכה bracha is in the field, right?
Right,
right, right. That's an interesting point. After you gathered it in, that's
a good point, right? As opposed to where it's naturally going to
grow. Okay. תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל. Tana devei Rabbi Yishmael. Oh, we
just did that. Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. ההולך למוד את גרנו,
Haholech lamod et gorno, somebody who's going to measure their their grain,
the threshing floor, the grain in their threshing floor,
אומר, omer, you say, יהי רצון מלפניך ה' אלוהינו שתשלח ברכה במעשה
ידינו. Yehi ratzon milfanecha Hashem eloheinu shetishlach bracha bema'aseh yadeinu.
May it be thy will God that you will give blessing into
the work of the labor of our hands. Okay, that's an interesting
question, right? This actually seems to be like a הלכה. halacha. This
is what you're supposed to do. This is an interesting question if
we actually פוסק posek this or not, but in what context we
פוסק posek this. התחיל למוד, Hitchil lamod, when
you begin to measure it, אומר, omer, ברוך השולח ברכה בכרי הזה,
Baruch hashole'ach bracha bekari hazeh, blessed is God who sends the blessing
into this into this, you know, a pile of grain. So what's
how's that different than what you first said? So the at least
the way the מהרש"א Maharsha explains it is, you know, I mean
it's interesting the way that when we say a ברכה, bracha, right,
particularly like in if you think about שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, a
ברכה bracha is normally blessed are you God, it's normally like a
what you would expect for something God has done, but often, you
know, there's a whole series of a ברכה bracha which is a
בקשה, bakasha, which you're blessing God for God's ability to do something
because you're really asking God to do it. ברוך אתה ה' רופא
חולי עמו ישראל, Baruch atah Hashem rofeh cholei amo Yisrael, bless you
God who heals the sick, you're asking God to heal the sick,
right? It's different of the ברכה bracha before שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei
where you say ברוך אתה ה' גאל ישראל Baruch atah Hashem ga'al
Yisrael for having redeemed Israel in the past. ברוך אתה ה' גואל
ישראל, Baruch atah Hashem go'el Yisrael, which is in שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh
Esrei, which is a request for God to redeem. So if you
think about it, it's interesting, right? What's the difference between the יהי
רצון מלפניך, yehi ratzon milfanecha, which is much more explicit, may it
be thy will, which is not the classic מטבע הברכה matbe'a haberacha
ברוך אתה ה', Baruch atah Hashem, but you're asking God please send
blessing, and then the ברכה bracha that you make, which is ברוך
אתה ה', Baruch atah Hashem, what's the
ברכה? bracha?
ברוך השולח ברכה בכרי הזה, Baruch hashole'ach bracha bekari hazeh, which is
basically asking for the same thing, please send a blessing, except you're
saying it in the מטבע הברכה matbe'a haberacha rather than the יהי
רצון. yehi ratzon. So it could be it is the same thing
except that, you know, it's when it's like when it's a little
bit you haven't begun it yet, right? It's you're going ההולך, haholech,
so that's more looking in the future. When it's sort of at
the moment, right, one is future. ברוך השולח Baruch hashole'ach is the
current, so you're asking God to do it but it's like in
the immediate present, it's like, you know, right now, right? So anyway,
so it seems like we're going future to present. All right. The
way the רמ"א Rama says it is the ברכה bracha is basically
a ברכה bracha of you're asking God you know, you're making the
ברכה bracha is almost like that no, no, but that like you
hope that your previous prayer was heard. Like it's with a type
of ביטחון, bitachon, I asked יהי רצון yehi ratzon and now I'm
saying ברוך השולח Baruch hashole'ach like I believe that God has heard
my prayer. But it could also be that now it's the it's
the present as opposed to before it was the future. Now, and
that's going to continue because now it's going to become the past.
Okay. So now it says מדד ואחר כך בירך, Madad ve'achar kach
beirach,
you measured the grain and then you said ברוך השולח ברכה בכרי
הזה, Baruch hashole'ach bracha bekari hazeh, so in that case הרי זו
תפילת שוא, harei zo tfillat shav, that's a blessing for naught because
what do you want to happen now? You measured it that there
were a hundred, you know, that there were a hundred units and
now you're going to make a ברכה bracha and you're going to
think there's going to come back tomorrow and it's going to be
120 units? Once you know the amount then, you know, then there
can't be any more natural growth. That'll become a נס גלוי. nes
galui. God's not going to do a נס גלוי. nes galui. So
what?
You're not talking about expressions of gratitude.
Yeah,
well,
you could say well, it's interesting because you could say ברוך ש...
You know השלח ברכה, beracha,
you know, would have been an expression of gratitude ששלח ברכה בכרי
הזה sheshalach beracha bakari hazeh or whatever. You know, what?
בענטשינג Benching הגומל? Hagomel? הגומל. Hagomel. הגומל לחייבים טובות. Hagomel lechayavim tovot.
That's interesting, that's in the present, but it's actually a thanks for
the past. But the point here is that yes, the use of
the present is a language of בקשה. bakasha. That's the standard way
it works, right? I mean, it is not only true because you
say בורא פרי העץ, borei pri ha'eitz, המוציא לחם מן הארץ, hamotzi
lechem min ha'aretz, which is in the present, which is a thanks
for, you know, but even there it's a little bit of a
thanks for the present, right? Well, I guess it could be the
same thing here. You've now measured, you see how much you have.
It's an interesting point, you know, but this is definitely understanding that
this נוסח nusach shows true, I guess the present language could be
a thanks and a request. גאל ישראל, Ga'al Yisrael, גואל ישראל, Go'el
Yisrael, you certainly see the difference there. But very often the present
is a thanks. Anyway, here it understands that it's not a thanks,
it's a request. And therefore, what sense does it make to ask
for the request once you see how much it is? Now of
course you could say maybe you want the request to be that
it doesn't rot, maybe you want, but still ברכה, Beracha, that would
more be protection. ברכה, beracha thank you, ברכה beracha suggests increase. Okay,
the grain is not going to magically increase. You're not going to
come back tomorrow and it's going to be more than you had.
Okay, so this really just the idea that God will allow the
amount to increase if you're not paying attention and looking, then it'll
be like a נס נסתר, nes nistar, but it won't be a
נס גלוי. nes galuy. So at this stage you can no longer
make a ברכה of בקשה bakasha for increase. That would be a
תפילת שוא. tefillat shav. ולפי שאין הברכה מצויה לא בדבר השקול ולא
בדבר המדוד, Ulefi she'ein haberacha metzuya lo bidvar hashakul velo bidvar hamadud,
for
the blessing will not increase, will not be found in something that
is weighed or measured, ולא בדבר המנוי velo bidvar hamannuy or counted,
אלא בדבר הסמוי מן העין, ela bidvar hasamuy min ha'ayin, hidden from
the eye. שנאמר, Shene'emar, right, which is really again not this עין
הרע ayin hara concern, this sense of that it has to be,
you know, God has to work sort of, you know, behind the
scenes. שנאמר יצו ה' אתך את הברכה באסמיך. Shene'emar yetzav Hashem itcha
et haberacha be'asamecha. Okay,
so that was a nice little digression of a couple of statements
of רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak about, you know, money and investment and
so on, and also, you know, things should be hidden from the
eye if you want them to be
blessed.
Yes. That's part of it. So you know, we were talking about
what is a good שמירה shmira or not. So let's say the
physical, yeah, give me a thousand dollars, all right? I'll put it
in the bank. What? I'll just put it in the bank.
Yeah, well that might be possible. They didn't have banks. So let's
take a look. Yeah, let's take a look. Okay, so now we're
getting back to this question about what is good שמירה shmira for
money. So in the משנה Mishna we said basically it means that
the money should be in your front pocket, not in your back
pocket. Okay, אמר שמואל. Amar Shmuel. Now שמואל Shmuel is going to
go one step further than the, like than you know, the משנה
Mishna or just read the משנה Mishna in an extreme. אמר שמואל
כספים אין להם שמירה אלא בקרקע. Amar Shmuel kesafim ein lahem shmira
ela be'karka. כספים Kesafim can only be protected if you dig them,
if you dig a hole in the ground and you bury them
in the ground. Right, obviously they are a high... what? In land?
Well actually it's good that you mention that because the מהרש"א Maharsha
suggests, it's not פשט, pshat, but the מהרש"א Maharsha does suggest that
one of the reasons of רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak of שליש בקרקע
shlish be'karka means you put a third in the ground, you bury
it in the ground. It connects to this statement of שמואל. Shmuel.
There you go, ta-da. Okay anyway, so he says look, you know,
money is, you know, I'm sure there were things that had higher
value, you know, like you know diamonds or whatever, pearls, whatever, but
money is a high amount of value for a small, you know,
for like a very highly concentrated value. So obviously it's a big
attraction for thieves. Okay, and that's why we had the statement before
about, you know, don't keep it behind you. So שמואל Shmuel takes
it to the next point. You know, any- in your house, what
happens? If thieves break into your house, they're going to tear up
your house top to bottom and they're going to look for the
money, and there's only so many like hiding places, you know, they
look in the mattress, they look in whatever. So what you gotta
do is you gotta bury it somewhere in the ground. They're not
going to start digging up the whole ground, so that's the only
safe place to hide the money. Okay, אמר רבא ומודה שמואל בערב
שבת בין השמשות. Amar Rava u'modeh Shmuel be'erev Shabbat bein hashemashot. Now
that's if you're watching somebody's money and they gave it to you
right on שבת, Shabbat, right before, you know, sunset. דלא אטרחוהו רבנן.
Delo atrachuhu rabanan. The rabbis did not demand that you go ahead
and you bury it, so there, that actually, you know, if you
bury it- if you hide it somewhere else, that would be considered
acceptable. Now obviously it can't be literally בין השמשות bein hashemashot because
then it's not דלא אטרחוהו רבנן, delo atrachuhu rabanan, then it's חילול
שבת chillul Shabbat to start digging the hole. But it means, and
also, what do you mean דלא אטרחוהו רבנן? delo atrachuhu rabanan? Even
if it's five minutes before שבת, Shabbat, you know, I can't do
it because I would be violating שבת Shabbat if I started digging
the hole. So it must mean like, okay, if a half hour
before שבת. Shabbat. Theoretically you could drop everything you're doing, stop working
on your טשולנט, cholent, stop doing this, stop doing that, don't take
a shower, don't whatever, just dig a hole right now. So that
they did not require. Now that's interesting because that means that the
standard of care, and this goes back to an important point of
the משנה, Mishna, is not just a reflection of the necessary care
needed to prevent the loss against a certain, you know, likelihood that
it'll get lost. Because the standard of care also to some degree
is shaped by what is the convention of the standard, right? What
is sort of דרך השומרים. derech hashomrim. That's what the משנה Mishna
says. So it could be that in reality, and that could go
higher or lower. Look, it doesn't matter is it ערב שבת erev
Shabbat or is it not ערב שבת. erev Shabbat. If I don't
bury it in the ground, thieves could break in. There's the same
risk. Okay, I'm exposing it to the same risk, but under certain...
circumstances, okay, it's not, you know, it's not reasonable to demand it
of you, it's not דרך השומרים, derech hashomrim, and it's not a
reasonable demand, so therefore you've done your duty even if you haven't
protected it against that degree of risk, because under these circumstances, your
duty... that's not your duty under these circumstances, only under other circumstances,
okay? So that's important, right? I'll just tie that into a point
we mentioned yesterday. Remember yesterday we talked about the shepherd going back
to town for his lunch break and then something happened? Well, that's
pretty irresponsible. Wolves and lions come during your lunch break as well,
right? It's not like you can have kept them protected from the
risk when you go back. But nevertheless, when you're doing דרך השומרים,
derech hashomrim, that can serve to limit your degree of care. There's
a certain question about like when is that duty and how is
that duty shaped by the norm. So of course we start by
the idea of reasonably protecting them against a certain degree of risk,
but then that can be shaped by דרך השומרים. derech hashomrim. Okay,
so ערב שבת erev Shabbos you do not have to start go
bury digging holes in your backyard. Okay, so then it says like
this: ואי
שהה למוצאי שבת v’ee sheha l’motzoei Shabbos שיעור למקברינהו ולא קברינהו. shiur
l’mikbrinhu v’lo kavrinhu. However, if it was מוצאי שבת motzoei Shabbos and
you waited and you know it was a half hour and you
could have, you had the time to bury it and that wasn't
the first thing that you did, מחייב, mechayav, and then it got
stolen, then you are מחייב. mechayav. Okay, because as soon as שבת
Shabbos is over, this has to be your first responsibility.
וצורבא מרבנן הוא, v’tzurba mei’rabanan hu, they did as torches. Now, if
the person who gave you the money is a תלמיד חכם, talmid
chacham, then סבר, savar, then you have a reason to say why
you did not immediately want to bury it מוצאי שבת. motzoei Shabbos.
דלמא מיבעי ליה זוזי להבדלתא, dilma mibai lei zuzei l’havdalata, maybe he
wants the money for to buy some wine for הבדלה. havdala. Okay,
now why he has to be a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, but
רש"י Rashi sort of says, you know, maybe they're very מקפיד makpid
to do הבדלה על הכוס. havdala al hakos. So and
so therefore, which is funny because you could do it on, you
know, חמר מדינה. chamar medina. So maybe again that's a normal person
would do it on חמר מדינה chamar medina but he wants to
spend the extra money, get some wine. You know, again, it's pretty
funny like, he didn't buy wine for שבת Shabbos because you need
wine for קידוש kiddush on שבת. Shabbos. Anyway, somehow that's a reasonable
explanation of why you didn't run to bury it. And then if
it gets stolen, you're not held responsible.
They might be coming, yeah, sorry I didn't spell that out, they
might be coming to ask you for the money back or for
some of the money back to buy some wine. Okay. מהו דתימא
הבדלתא? mahu d’teima havdalata?
What?
No, that I should go ahead and dig a hole and bury
it just to have to undig the hole or whatever? I wanted
to wait an hour before burying it because I thought there was
a chance he would come and ask for it back during that
hour. That's reasonable.
I mean, it's reasonable if it happens a lot.
Right. I don't know what to say. All right.
If you've left over, you know, the five dollars or whatever it
would have taken to buy... well maybe it's true if you only
need to leave over that amount of money that was needed for
the wine. All right. והאידנא דשכיחי גשושי. v’haidna d’sh’chichi gashushei.
Nowadays, says the גמרא, Gemara, that there are people that bang on
the ground and try to feel, check where you've recently dug up
the earth. Okay.
לית להו שמירה אלא בשמי קורה. leit lehu shmira ela b’shmei kora.
The only place you can hide them now is like in the
rafters. Of course, you know, thank you very much for announcing where
the next place is to look.
האידנא
דשכיחי פרומאי. idna d’sh’chichi frumai. And now that there are people that
basically break through the roof to get into the rafters, to get
into the like attic, לית להו שמירה אלא ביני אורבי. leit lehu
shmira ela beini orbei. The only place to hide them is in
the bricks of the house, like you take out a brick and
you know, you put it in, you bury it in the wall.
What is that word פרומאי? frumai? There's a word that means guys
who break...
I don't know what to tell you. Look at רש"י, Rashi, okay?
רש"י Rashi says,
what does רש"י Rashi say?
שוברי תקרה, shovrei tikra, see that? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
okay. אמר רבא ומודי שמואל. amar Rava u’modi Shmuel. Now שמואל Shmuel
says that you have to bury them in the ground. He
agrees בכותל. b’kotel. Now don't say, wait a minute, I thought we
buried it in the wall? שמואל Shmuel says it has to be
in the ground. No, no, no. שמואל Shmuel would be okay in
the wall because again, people are not going to start ripping down
your wall to see as they break into the house, you know,
they're... you know,
it's going to be safe in the wall as well. והאידנא, v’haidna,
but not really, says the גמרא. Gemara. Because nowadays דשכיחי טפוחאי, d’sh’chichi
tapuchai, from the word טפח, tefach, like you know, to like your
hand or your fist, people that are basically knock against the wall
and listen for where it's hollow and where you might have removed
the bricks. Okay. לית להו שמירה אלא בטפחא סמוך לקרקע. leit lehu
shmira ela b’tefcha samuch l’karka. You have to... no, no, not in
the ground though, in the wall near the base of the wall.
Because if it's near the base of the wall, you can't like
hear the hollow, you can't presumably if you dug it out and
if you took out the brick and put it back in. אי
נמי בטפחא סמוך לשמי קורה, ee nami b’tefcha samuch l’shmei kora, or
the opposite, so the brick, you know, the row of bricks right
near the ceiling. Okay. אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרב יוסף לרב
אשי. amar lei Rav Acha brei d’Rav Yosef l’Rav Ashi. So רב
אחא Rav Acha the son of רב יוסף Rav Yosef said
to רב אשי. Rav Ashi. התם תנן. hatam tnan. Over there by
פסחים Pesachim we teach, חמץ שנפלה עליו מפולת. chametz shenafela alav mapolet.
If a wall collapsed on a piece of חמץ, chametz, הרי הוא
כמבוער, harei hu k’mevuar, you can treat it as it's already destroyed
and you don't have to get rid of it before פסח. Pesach.
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר כל שאין הכלב יכול לחפש אחריו, Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel omer kol she’ein hakelev yachol l’chapes acharav, as long
as a dog can't dig it out. ותנא כמה חפיסת הכלב. v’tana
kama chafisat hakelev.
how deep down would it be that a dog cannot dig it
out? ג' טפחים gimmel tefachim three טפחים tefachim which is I don't
know nine inches deep in the rubble. So הכא מאי hacha mai
here when we said that you're supposed to bury it in the
ground, going back to the ground with all the Gemara's modifications, how
deep do you have to bury it? מי בעינן שלושה טפחים mi
ba'inan shlosha tefachim does it have to be three טפחים tefachim deep
into the ground? או לא o lo or not? אמר ליה amar
lei he says to him the obvious answer, no. התם משום ריחא
hatam mishum reicha there it's food, it smells, and the dog is
going to go for it. ובעינן ג' טפחים u-va'inan gimmel tefachim you
need it to be very deep. הכא משום אכסויי מאינא hacha mishum
iksuyei me-eina here the money doesn't smell, it's just making it hidden
from the eye, like the Gemara before, some מניין, minayin, לא בעינן
ג' טפחים lo ba'inan gimmel tefachim and it does not need to
be so deep. וכמה ve-kama so how deep? אמר רב ספרא amar
Rav Safra נסיכא טפח nesicha tefach
okay, one טפח tefach deep. Good. So now we know where at
least according to שמואל Shmuel and it seems like the Gemara is
sort of agreeing with שמואל, Shmuel, it's not even enough to keep
the money in your front pocket, right, you have to keep it
dug into the earth. Presumably, a safe in a bank would be
consistent with that. Okay. אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav Yosef,
I know, so that's going to be the interesting thing that we're
going to get to. And the question is: is less than this
פשיעה? peshia? It sounds to be, because we didn't say this is
just for a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. So it sounds like that
even though we normally say that a שומר חינם, shomer chinam, right,
is פטור patur in גניבה, geneiva, right, it sounds like we're saying
that's only a פטור patur in גניבה geneiva if you protected it
appropriately, right? But if you leave it out and exposed, then even
a שומר חינם, shomer chinam, that's negligent. And it sounds like anything
less than burying it in the ground according to this approach would
be considered negligence for a שומר חינם. shomer chinam. So you know,
good way of protecting your money is give it to somebody to
watch for you. I mean, I guess that's the business of banks,
you know. So then people go into business for charging. Now, תוספות,
Tosafot, now look at תוספות. Tosafot. Shh. Yeah, תוספות, Tosafot, look at
תוספות Tosafot before you hit the Gemara. אמר שמואל צריכין להם שמירה.
amar Shmuel tzrichin lahem shemira. תוספות Tosafot says the following. צריך עיון
tzarich iyun אם שמרן בקרקע ונגנבו משם אם שומר שכר חייב. im
shamran be-karka ve-nignevu mi-sham im shomer sachar chayav. Okay, so I get
that less than this is considered to be פשיעה. peshia. All right.
I think רש"י Rashi even says that explicitly. Let me just find
the previous רש"י. Rashi.
Yeah, רש"י Rashi says, if you look at רש"י Rashi four lines
down from the near lines: אין להם שמירה דאם לא שמרן ונגנבו
פשיעה היא. ein lahem shemira de-im lo shamran ve-nignevu peshia hi. Okay?
So less than burying them in the ground is פשיעה. peshia. Let's
say you bury them in the ground and some גנב ganav manages
to find them. Are you is that already an אונס? oness? Are
you like פטור patur as a שומר שכר, shomer sachar, right? Is
it like one extreme or the other? Either you're negligent or it's
a complete אונס, oness, right? There's no middle ground. That's what תוספות
Tosafot wants to know, logically, if you bury them in the ground
and somebody manages to dig up the ground and find it, again,
unless you sort of left signs and left the earth obvious, you
know, or whatever, you would think that that would be an אונס.
oness. Okay? So תוספות Tosafot says, would you be פטור? patur? ובפרק
הכונס משמע דחייב. u-ve-Perek Ha-Kones mashma de-chayav. דפריך לרב יוסף de-parich le-Rav
Yosef and it goes on and on. He says and then תוספות
Tosafot leads תוספות Tosafot to a whole question about when we normally
say that a שומר שכר shomer sachar is חייב chayav for גניבה,
geneiva, is it even if it's a גניבה geneiva that he's an
אונס oness about? Okay? 'Cause and תוספות Tosafot says some גמרות Gemarot
that sound like it, which is a little crazy, 'cause you would
think it's not the question about yes גניבה geneiva or not גניבה.
geneiva. It's a question about negligent, fully negligent, somewhat negligent, total אונס,
oness, right? But you have here this irony. On the one hand,
a שומר חינם shomer chinam can be חייב chayav for גניבה geneiva
if you're irresponsible, if you don't bury them in the ground, right?
And then the other question is, well, can a שומר שכר shomer
sachar be פטור patur because then we would say if you did
bury them in the ground it would be אונס. oness. Or we
would just say, no, by virtue of the fact that it's considered
a גניבה, geneiva, you're חייב chayav even though it's an אונס. oness.
So תוספות Tosafot obviously is not happy with that conclusion. We'd like
to say it's not some magic about being called גניבה geneiva that
makes you חייב chayav as a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. It has
to do with degree of negligence. Okay, but that's what this big
תוספות Tosafot tries to work out, conflicting evidence whether a שומר שכר
shomer sachar is חייב chayav for גניבה באונס. geneiva be-oness. Yes.
Right, so that's what we said that ליסטים מזוין listim mezuyan is
אונס. oness.
So that's what תוספות Tosafot worked out.
It's clear that it's on you.
It's clear that ליסטים מזוין listim mezuyan is a גניבה geneiva that's
an אונס oness that a שומר שכר shomer sachar is פטור patur
in. But תוספות Tosafot says it sounds like from a lot of
גמרות Gemarot that other גניבות אונס geneivot oness a שומר שכר shomer
sachar is חייב chayav in. And he doesn't and he says he
can't figure out why we should make such a difference. So that's
what תוספות Tosafot tries to figure out. Okay? But so look at
the תוספות, Tosafot, okay, we'll tell you some other time. But anyway,
that's the issue. It could be the simple reading though is that
less than burying it in the ground, you're negligent. Once you bury
it in the ground, you're אונס. oness. There's like no middle ground.
Let's get back to the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara says like
this.
ההוא גברא דאפקיד זוזי גבי חבריה hahu gavra de-afkid zuzei gabei chavreih
a person entrusted some money to his friend. אותבינהו בצריפא דאורבני otvinhu
be-tzrifa de-urbani he put it in
the duck blind, you know,
in those Rashi says it's like the hut that they have out
in the field for like hunting birds. Okay? איגנוב ignuv
and it was stolen from there. אמר רב יוסף amar Rav Yosef
אע"ג דלענין גנבי נטירותא היא af al gav de-le-inyan ganavei netiruta hi
even though that place is protected against גנבים, ganavim, like nobody knows
where your various huts out in the field are that you go
for hunting duck, okay, or whatever you're hunting, so that's totally protected
from גנבים, ganavim, לענין נורא פשיעותא היא le-inyan nura peshiuta hi it's
negligence in terms of fire. of the fire. I don't know, I
guess sometimes brush fires break out. Okay, so okay, but it wasn't
a fire, it was stolen, so you should be an אונס ones
for גניבה? gneivah? No, הוי תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס חייב. hava tchilato
bifshiya vesofo b'ones chayav. This is back to that. You were פושע
poshea by the fire and it ended by an אונס ones that
it was stolen. And again, the key I told you when we
did this last night is, as long as some argument can be
made that it was stolen because it was there rather than somewhere
else. Yes, the act of putting it there was not irresponsible as
far as גניבה gneivah was concerned. But it shouldn't have been there
because it was irresponsible for fire. And it's possible the reason it
was stolen was that it was there rather than where it should
have been. So that's תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס. tchilato bifshiya vesofo b'ones.
Okay, yes the גניבה gneivah was an אונס, ones, but there was
a degree of negligence that could be attributed to what happened and
therefore you're
חייב. chayav. וסופו באונס חייב. vesofo b'ones chayav. איכא דאמרי ika d'amri
some say אף על גב דלעניין נורא פשיעותא היא, af al gav
d'l'inyan nura p'shiyutahi, it was the opposite ruling, even though as far
as fire's concerned it's negligent, ולעניין גנבי נטירותא היא ul'inyan ganve netirutahi
as far as גניבה gneivah it is protected, תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס
פטור. tchilato bifshiya vesofo b'ones patur. And when you're and when you
start with a פשיעה pshiya in one area and it's an אונס
ones in another area you're פטור. patur. So that's the question, how
do we פסקן? pasken? והלכתא v'hilcheta so finally, see Michael left, that's
too bad, the גמרא Gemara finally is פסקנינג paskening for us, והלכתא
תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס חייב. v'hilcheta tchilato bifshiya vesofo b'ones chayav. You
are חייב. chayav. Except if you look at תוספות Tosafot you'll see
that there was actually some debate about what the גירסא girsa in
the גמרא Gemara was. Okay, so some people have the גירסא פטור.
girsa patur. Okay, but nevertheless תוספות Tosafot says all the evidence from
other גמרא Gemara is that we rule תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס חייב.
tchilato bifshiya vesofo b'ones chayav. All right.
Now the גמרא Gemara says like this, ההוא גברא hahu gavra another
interesting case. A certain person דאפקיד זוזי גבי חבריה. d'afkid zuzei gabei
chavrei. He gave some money to his friend to watch for him.
אמר ליה amar leh הב
לי זוזי. hav li zuzei. He said to him like a month
later, let me have my money back. אמר ליה amar leh לא
ידענא היכא אותבינהו. lo yadana heicha otvinhu. Oh I forgot where I
put them. So actually he could have said I listened to שמואל,
Shmuel, I buried them in the ground and I covered them up
real well so I didn't leave any evidence and I have no
idea where I left them. Okay,
so what? Where'd you park? Where'd you park? Right exactly. So אתו
לקמיה דרבה atu l'kamei d'Rabbah they came to רבה Rabbah and אמר
ליה amar leh כל לא ידענא פשיעותא היא kol lo yadana p'shiyuta
hi anything I don't know where it is, that's negligence, okay? It's
not lost, it's misplaced, but it doesn't matter, it's negligence. זיל שלים,
zil shleim, go pay him up. You know if you find the
money you keep it, but right now it's lost due to your
negligence.
That's a very annoying פסק. psak. What?
If you what can I tell you? ההוא גברא דאפקיד זוזי גבי
חבריה. hahu gavra d'afkid zuzei gabei chavrei. Right.
A certain person I know every time I tell my wife I
can't find my keys, I can't find my whatever, כל לא ידענא
פשיעותא היא. kol lo yadana p'shiyuta hi. ההוא גברא דאפקיד זוזי גבי
חבריה. hahu gavra d'afkid zuzei gabei chavrei.
A certain person entrusted money to his friend. אשלמינהו לאימיה. ashalminhu l'imei.
אשלמינהו ashalminhu
he handed them over to his mother. He gave it to his
mother. He said here's some money, watch this for me mom. ואותבינהו
בקרטליתא v'otvinhu b'kartsilita
and she put it in some type of a box. Okay? ואיגנוב
v'ignov and the box was stolen. So she didn't put it in
the ground. אמר רבא amar Rava היכי נדיינו דייני להאי דינא, heichi
nadaynu dayanei l'hai dina, how should the judges decide this case? ניימא
ליה לדידיה זיל שלים, neima leh l'didei zil shleim, tell the guy
who was supposed to watch this go pay, you're irresponsible. You gave
it to your mother, you should have buried it. אמר amar he
can say כל המפקיד על דעת
אשתו ובניו הוא מפקיד, kol hamafkid al daat ishto uvanav hu mafkid,
whoever entrusts, whoever gives something over to be watched, understands that the
guy might give it to his wife or his kids to watch
and he implicitly says that's okay, they can watch for you, that's
implicit. Of course now we're also learning that you go up a
generation not just down a generation. You can also give it to
your mom. I don't know, maybe it's only if you're living with
your mom or something. I don't know. Anyway that somehow was acceptable.
He was not negligent. It wasn't שומר שמסר לשומר חייב. shomer shemasar
l'shomer chayav.
The giving to the mother wasn't negligent, fine. Okay, but let's take
a look at the care the mother exerted. ניימא לה לאימיה זיל
שלימי, neima lah l'imei zil shleimi, say to the mother go pay.
אמרה amra לא אמר לי דלאו דידיה נינהו דאקברינהו. lo amar li
d'lav deidei ninhu d'akvinhu.
He didn't tell me it wasn't his money. I thought my son
was giving me his own money to watch. So own money, you
know I put it in my little box here in the kitchen.
If I knew it was somebody else's money that we had a
duty of care, I would have buried it in the ground. So
I wasn't negligent. Okay, now if that's true you should say then
who was negligent here? The son, right? Because the son should say
he's responsible to make it clear to his mother what the circumstances
are so she knows the degree of care that's needed. And if
he's not, then he's being negligent.
Okay, so ניימא ליה, neima leh, so let's say to him אמאי
לא אמרת לה amai lo amart lah why didn't you tell her
that it was your money?
אמר amar he'll say כל שכן דכי אמינא לה דדידי נינהו kol
shekein d'ki amina lah d'didi ninhu I thought it was better not
to tell her it was somebody else's money. If she thought it
was mine טפי מזדהרא בהו tfei mizdahara behu she'd be even more
careful with it. Which is like a great question, right? Are you
more careful with your own property or somebody else's property? So he
sent her, right, you know if I think it's my mom, my
mom would want to protect my money more than somebody else's. I'll
let her think it's mine. Okay, so now so nobody so so
if that was like a reasonable assumption that he should have assumed
that his mother would have thought that way, right, then he wasn't
sort of negligent, he was giving it to her assuming with the
right to whom she'd do the right level of care.
She... Nevertheless, I know you ask me, I still think it's the
son's responsibility, right? You made an assumption that it would, but given
that you had the duty of care, you shouldn't have relied on
an assumption that
reasonably other people would not have acted in that way. You needed
to spell things out. Okay, so it seems to be pretty clear
that he should be held responsible for his negligence or that we
should treat it as he was negligent. Let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says with this.
אלא אמר רבא, Ella amar Rava, so רבא Rava said, but the
גמרא Gemara is making it sound like nobody was negligent. Everybody had
a right to assume what they assumed and nobody was negligent. He
had a right to give it to his mother assuming she would
care for it. She had a right to assume what's hers and
she didn't have a duty of care. Nobody was at fault. אלא
אמר רבא משתבע איהו דהנהו זוזי מסרתינהו לאימיה. Ella amar Rava mishtaba
ihu de-hanei zuzei asminhu l'imei. Let him swear that he gave it
over to his mother, okay, ומשתבעא אימיה דהנהו זוזי בקרטיליא אותבינהו u-mishtaba
imei de-hanei zuzei asvinhu b'kartilya
and let her swear that she put it in the
box ואיגנו v'ignu and then it was stolen from there ופטור. u-patur.
Basically, as long as we can establish the facts of what happened,
we're going to assume that nobody was actually negligent. It's funny that
you don't make them swear, let him swear that he assumed his
mother would do the duty of care, let his mother swear that
she assumed that it
was her that it wasn't somebody else's money. But anyway, somehow those
which are considered the key questions of what makes you liable or
not, you're not swearing to. You're swearing to the facts and we're
sort of saying nobody was really negligent. Yes.
I wonder if they wanted to make sure neither of them stole
it, so they're making them swear.
Right, so that's a good point. Why are they swearing to this?
Generates the right question. This probably gets back to that statement of
רב נחמן Rav Nachman that a שומר shomer has to swear that
it's אינו ברשותו. eino bireshuso. So in addition to swearing it was
stolen, right, you're also swearing that it's like אינו ברשותו. eino bireshuso.
He's swearing that he gave it to somebody else and he was
a שומר שמסר לשומר shomer she-masar l'shomer but within legitimate parameters because
he gave it to his mother. Right. But it is interesting that
this is a case where nobody was negligent. By the way, תוספות
Tosafot raises a very important question about שומר שמסר לשומר, shomer she-masar
l'shomer, which תוספות Tosafot says let's say the mother was negligent. Okay.
And he wasn't, like he was a שומר שמסר לשומר, shomer she-masar
l'shomer, he gave it to his kid, he gave it to his
mother, right, he could assume that they would be responsible, they were
negligent. Who's liable to the original owner for the negligence of the
if you had a right to give it to the second guy,
you give it to your kids, your wife, your mother, your husband,
whatever, okay, are they now חייב chayav directly to the owner or
are they an extension of
you and you're חייב chayav to the owner? So this גמרא Gemara
breaks it down like if the mother was negligent, the mother is
חייב chayav to the owner and not me. But תוספות Tosafot says
no. That just means also the mother is חייב, chayav, okay, but
once I am the שומר, shomer, even if I have a right
to sort of give it to somebody else to watch for me,
I remain fully
responsible. And if they're פושע, poshea, that's also on me. Okay. So
it's not clear from the גמרא, Gemara, but that's an important point
that תוספות Tosafot makes. Okay.
But the mother's also חייב chayav because she did it intentionally?
Well, no, it means that the guy I mean the guy can
sort of like it's sort of like a בבא קמא Bava Kamma
case, you know, רצה מזה גובה רצה מזה גובה, ratza mizeh goveh
ratza mizeh goveh, like can the guy go to one if he
doesn't have the money go to the other? Questions like which one
does he go to first? Anyway, if you want to take a
look at it, תוספות, Tosafot, he says like this: כל המפקיד על
דעת אשתו ובניו הוא מפקיד. kol hamaphkid al da'as ishto u-vanav hu
maphkid. אמר רבנו תם Amar Rabbeinu Tam דהיינו לענין שאינו יכול לומר
את מהימנת לי בשבועה
ולא
האיך. de-hainu l'inyan she-eino yachol lomar at meheimenat li bishvuah v'lo ha-ich.
The point is is that that means that you weren't like violated
the rules of שומר שמסר לשומר shomer she-masar l'shomer and you're automatically
liable for handing it over. אבל אם
פשעו, aval im pash'u, if the second party you gave it to,
your kids, your spouse or whatever were פושע, poshea, אפילו אין להם
מה לשלם, afilu ein lahem mah l'shalem, even if the owner can't
go
to your spouse or kids because they don't have any money, ישלם
הנפקד, yeshalem hanifkad, the original guy, it's his responsibility for their negligence.
דאם לא כן, d'im lo ken, תוספות Tosafot says, כל מה שהפקיד
אצל בעל הבית תבא אשתו ותאכל ותפטר. kol mah she-hiphkid etzel baal
ha-bayis tavo ishto v'sochal v'tipater. Look, I got a great way. Give
me your objects to watch, I give it to my wife, she'll
go ahead and literally תוספות Tosafot says she'll consume them and then
she doesn't have any money because she's my wife, right, so קני
אישה קנה בעלה, kani isha kanah baalah, so there's no way you
can collect from her and you can't collect from me either because
it wasn't me who did it, it was my wife who did
it. Okay. So clearly תוספות Tosafot says if you're taking it, you
at the end of the day retain respons- you're fully responsible for
whatever happens, alright. So שומר שמסר לשומר, shomer she-masar l'shomer, you're not
חייב chayav for the act of giving it over if you are
giving it to your spouse or kids or mother according to this,
but if anything happens that's through their negligence, then that's your responsibility
as well.
Okay. ולא האיך. v'lo ha-ich.
What? At the end of that it says ולא האיך v'lo ha-ich
and not the other guy.
Ah, but not the other guy.
Okay. Alright.
But isn't that because the reason he's allowed to give it to
them is because they are sort of deemed to be an extension
of him? Yeah, but it's not like I gave it to my
next-door neighbor.
Right. But if it were a
case like if you remember the גמרא Gemara had a case before
that שומר שמסר לשומר shomer she-masar l'shomer would be allowed if generally
I entrusted to ראובן, Reuven, ראובן Reuven wasn't
around. Once it's any scenario in which you are not violating the
rules of שומר שמסר לשומר, Shomer shemasar l'shomer, it's acceptable to give
it to the other person, nevertheless you remain, you know, ultimately responsible,
right? Because you're the one who accepted the responsibility. שומר שמסר
לשומר Shomer shemasar l'shomer means if I didn't have a right to
give it to somebody else, then even if an אונס oness happened,
I'm חייב. chayav. Okay, שומר shomer when when it's allowed, it's my
spouse, it's my kids, it's my mother, it's the guys that the
owners usually give it to who happen to show up, I'm allowed
to, it means that the act of giving did not automatically translate
into liability. But if anything does happen due to negligence or whatever,
ultimately it's on my shoulders, okay? Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara
brings up a very important point that we had not discussed earlier.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: ההוא אפוטרופא דיתמי, Hahu
apotropos d'yasmi, a
certain overseer executor of the estate of orphans, דזבין להו תורא ליתמי,
d'zaven lehu tora l'yasmi, he bought an ox for the orphans with
their money, you know, made an investment, to have presumably he's going
to have the property plowed or whatever, ומסריה לבקרא, u'mashlei l'bakra, and
he gave it over to the cowherd, okay? לא
הוה ליה כיכי ושיני, Lo hava lei kichi v'shinei, it happened that
nobody checked this cow before buying it, and it didn't have like
incisors and molars למיכל l'meichal to eat. ומית, U'meis, and guess what?
It died. So the cowherd had it, you know, he gave it
the food, he wasn't checking which cows, he had a thousand cows.
This one didn't eat, it died of starvation. אמר רמי בר חמא,
Amar Rami bar Chama, היכא נדיינוה להאי דינא? heicha nidaina l'hai dina?
How should judges decide this case? ניימא ליה לאפוטרופא, Neima lei l'apotropos,
say to the אפוטרופא, apotropos, זיל שלים, zil shalim, go pay the
orphans because you were irresponsible, you gave it over to the cowherd
and you should have checked the cow beforehand. אמר, Amar, אנא לבקרא
מסרתיה, ana l'bakra masartei, that wasn't my responsibility, I gave it over
to the cowherd, the care of it is the cowherd's, I wasn't
negligent. ניימא ליה לבקרא, Neima lei l'bakra, say to the cowherd, זיל
שלים, zil shalim, go pay. אמר, Amar, אנא בהדי תורי אוקימתיה, ana
bahadei tori ukmintei, what do you mean? I did everything I'm supposed
to do with him. I put him with all the other cows
ושדאי להו, v'shadai lehu, I threw food out to all of the
cows. לא ידענא
דלא אכל, Lo yadan d'lo achal, so
I didn't know it wouldn't eat, which just raises the question: okay,
so who has who is assumed if the level of care that
you assume from the cowherd is not to make sure that every
animal is eating, right? The level of care is just make sure
like, you know, that you give them the food, so then it
wasn't his responsibility. And then presumably it is the responsibility of the
אפוטרופא. apotropos. Right, I mean this is a pretty straightforward question here.
What is the normal standard of care that you expect from the
cowherd and what's the normal sort of precautions, you know, or where
do we assume responsibility lies in terms of the owners? Okay, so
let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes. מכדי, Michdi, בקרא שומר שכר
דיתמי הוא, bakra shomer sachar d'yasmi hu, the cowherd
is the orphans' שומר שכר, shomer sachar, he's paid for his work,
okay, איבעי ליה לעיוני, itba'ei lei l'iyunei, so the גמרא Gemara says:
so if there's some ambiguity, the higher level of care is, you
know, you're paying me to watch your cow, I can't just say,
'oh, I just throw it the food,' because I'm being paid it
means that I have to realize sometimes things go wrong and I
need to, you know, have that extra level of care.
אי איכא פסידא דיתמי הכי נמי, Ee ika pseda d'yasmi hachi nami,
you know what, you're right. If it was as the case as
we described, the cow died because it wasn't eating, then the guy
who was being paid was the guy who was responsible to make
sure everything was going all right and the cowherd would be liable.
So if the orphans were the one who lost out, it would
be clear, the cowherd is liable. But the orphans didn't lose out.
How did the orphans not lose out?
So it says like this: הא הכא במאי עסקינן דליכא פסידא דיתמי,
Ha hacha b'mai askinan d'leka pseda d'yasmi, they didn't lose out. How
did that happen? Their cow died. No, דאשכחוה למרא דתורא ושקול יתמי
זוזי מיניה. d'ashkechu l'marei d'tora v'shakal yasmi zuzai minei. The orphans found
the original owner of the cow and they said, 'Hey buddy, the
cow died, it didn't have any incisors and molars. What type of
a cow is that?' So he said, 'Hey we want a refund.'
So he's like מקח טעות, mekach taus, we want a refund.
So he said, 'Fine, here's your money back.' So he gave them
the money back. So now he gave them the money back, retroactively
it was a מקח טעות. mekach taus. Whose cow was it when
it died?
The original owner's. So now the question is: is the cowherd liable
to the original owner, right, because he never contracted with the original
owner? It's sort of like ושומר שמסר לשומר, v'shomer shemasar l'shomer, it's
sort of like, you know, when the shomer— when I rented from
you and lent it to somebody else, how much, you know, is
that person responsible to me or responsible to the original owner? So
here it turned out to be a מקח טעות, mekach taus, the
cowherd was watching the owner's cow without ever having entered into any
contractual relationship with the owner. So who's liable, okay? Yes, exactly. So
it says like this. Okay. Yes.
Wait a second. The original owner had this cow without teeth.
Yeah. And it was alive. How do you keep it alive?
I don't know, I don't know.
I don't know what to say. Maybe it was a calf, maybe
it was just born.
Can we
let's read the גמרא Gemara then you can complain.
I now have so expectation of the בקר, bakar, of the cowboy,
of the guy.
Yeah, okay, let's take a look. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like
this. Okay,
אלא מאן קטעי, ella man katai, who's making the claim here? מרי
דתורא, mari de-tora, the original owner קטעי, katai, he's making the claim.
So the גמרא Gemara says איבעי ליה לאודוען. ibaye leh le-hoduan. So
they're saying he should have told me. You had my cow, it
didn't have molars. You were the cowherd who was being paid. You
should have been on top of this. And if there was a
problem, you should have told me and given it back to me
before it died. So גמרא Gemara says מאי מודעינן ליה מידע ידע
דמקח טעות הוה. mai modiyan leh meda yada de-mekach taut havah. So
what do you mean they have to let him know? He knew
it was a מקח טעות. mekach taut. He basically is giving the
kids their money back, presumably he knows what he sold them. What's
his claim that he was somehow somebody owes him anything? It was
his cow, he should have known. So גמרא Gemara says no, no,
no. בספסירא, be-safsera, we're dealing with a middleman דזבין מהכא ומזבין להכא.
de-zabin me-hacha u-mazbin le-hacha. He's not a farmer. Basically he goes to
ראובן, Reuven, buys the cow, turns around and sells it to שמעון
Shimon for a tidy profit. Okay? So that's why, that answers your
question though. How does he keep it alive? He didn't keep it
alive. ראובן Reuven was force feeding it, ראובן Reuven knew the problem,
ראובן Reuven hid the problem from the middleman. Probably not a good
businessman if you buy a cow without checking its mouth. Okay? Turned
around and sold it to שמעון Shimon who also didn't check its
mouth. Okay? So anyway, so this guy who is caught in the
middle now, who now שמעון Shimon or the kids want to get
their money back from, he says I had no idea that it
didn't have teeth. So I'm happy to reimburse the kids, you're right
I sold them a defective cow. But the cowherd should have told
me about that so I could have done something about it. I
didn't know that.
So the owner's gotta reimburse the ספסירא, safsera, that's what it's gotta
be.
Well, that's also true. Why doesn't he go back to... Yeah, but
for whatever reason that guy is long gone. Okay? He's out of
the picture. He's long gone. Okay? So I say, I'll do the
right thing, I'll reimburse the kids, it was unwitting to me but
I realize I sold them a defective cow, okay. But now I
want the cowherd to pay me because he should have seen what
was happening. Which is reasonable. Okay? So גמרא Gemara says like this:
הלכך משתבע איהו דלא הוה ידע ומשלים בקרא דמי בשר בזול. hilkach
mishtava ihu de-la havah yada u-mashlim bakra dmei basar bezol. And let
him swear that he did not know that it was missing the
teeth, because if he knew then he was fully liable for anything
that happened. He was ignorant, and therefore he could have said I
would have expected something from the
cowherd. And the cowherd pays him for wholesale value of the meat.
Not for the full value of the cow, but the wholesale value
of the meat. Now what type... רש''י Rashi says it's two-thirds of
the retail value. Now what type of crazy compromise is that? If
the cowherd is liable, he should pay him the full amount. So
רש''י Rashi says, well, says רש''י, Rashi, you know, it was a
little negligent, not a lot negligent. So we're not gonna make him
pay the full amount, you know, we're gonna make him pay two-thirds,
which is like we've never heard of that, a sliding scale. Either
you hit the threshold and you pay the full or you're below
the threshold and whatever and you pay zero. It's not like well
close, so pay two-thirds.
So תוספות Tosafot has a better answer. תוספות Tosafot says look,
what should the cowherd have done? If the cowherd was being responsible,
he would have said, oh my god, this cow isn't eating, it's
about to die. So what should he have done? What's the most
responsible thing to do? By the time you go and you tell
the owner or whatever, right, the cow's going to die. The most
responsible thing to do would have been שחט shecht it right there.
Turn it into meat. Okay? Of course, it's not during the market
time. You'd have to sell it wholesale at that stage. So what
you would be able to sell it for would be the דמי
בשר בזול. dmei basar bezol. So if you had done your responsibility,
this cow, you know, if you get it at the market at
the right time, you get five thousand dollars for it. But if
you would have slaughtered it right away and whatever, you know, at
least you could have saved and protected three thousand dollars. You were
not being responsible, you were not paying attention, you at least have
to pay me three thousand dollars because had you done your responsibility,
you would have protected at least the three thousand dollars of the
investment.
And the cowherd wasn't expected to anticipate a cow without molars, he's
expected to see
who's eating, who's now not eating, whatever. Now תוספות Tosafot says though,
the key question here is why is the cowherd responsible to the
owner he never contracted with him? And תוספות Tosafot revisits the משנה
Mishna at the beginning of the פרק, perek, which is, remember when
I rent it from somebody and lend it to someone else? And
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says כיצד הלה עושה סחורה בפרתו של חבירו?
keitzad halah oseh s'chora be-parato shel chaveiro? And the שואל shoel has
to pay the original owner. At the time we thought that that
was a moral sort of objection. How can I make business off
of somebody else's thing? But תוספות Tosafot actually says it might be
more than a moral objection. The reality, I rented, right, Eli's cow
and I lent it to David. David is now using Eli's cow.
That might reality, even though he never contracted with Eli, the reality
that he's using Eli's cow might create a
borrower relationship. The orphans, right, they bought it, they contracted with the
cowherd. It turned out it wasn't their cow, it turned out it
was the original owner's cow because it's going to be a מקח
טעות. mekach taut. But the fact that the cowherd is being paid
to watch the cow might obligate him to the whoever the owner
is, even if he didn't contract to the owner. So that's like
a really interesting question, right, about how these relationships can be created
de facto by context of whose cow are you watching, whose cow
are you renting or borrowing, even if you didn't enter into a
direct contractual relationship with that person. And that seems to be what's
going on here. Okay, so that's the- the cowherd is liable to
the original owners, even though there was no relationship- direct relationship with
him. Yes.
I must be missing something, but didn't we have the original owner
admitting there's a מקח טעות mekach taut to the יתומים? yetomim? Right.
But then as far as the בקרא bakra is concerned, he's swearing
that he doesn't know that it's a-
that it's- Right, even if he wasn't- even if he didn't engage
in fraud, it was still a מקח טעות. mekach taut. Right? If
I sell you a car that I never tested or whatever, I
mean it's with- it's- I'm not engaging in fraud, but you're entitled
to your money back, it wasn't- right when you go ahead and
you tell the car lot and you say I got the- the
object was defective, I'm returning it, fine, we have no hassles, no
return policy, whatever, they're not saying they misled you, they're just taking
responsibility they didn't send you the object you were asking for, you
know? Okay, so let's now finish this up. Okay, ההוא גברא דאפקיד
כישותא גבי חבריה. Hahu gavra de'afkid kishuta gabei chavreih.
Somebody gave some hops to his friend. הוה ליה לדידיה נמי כריא
דכישותא. Hava lei ledidei nami karya dekishuta.
He also was in the beer making business and had a pile
of hops. אמר ליה לסרסיה. Amar lei lesarsayeih. He said to his
like you know his-
his employee, the guy working in the- in the sort of you
know where with the beer, he said מהאי רמי. Meihai rami. Go
ahead and put the hops into the beer and take it from
this pile. And he showed him his own, you know, his pile,
not the- the stuff he was watching. Okay, אזל רמי מאידך. Azal
rami me'idach. He- he went and put the hops of the other
pile which didn't belong to the guy. Okay, אמר רב פפא היכי
נדיינוה להאי דינא. Amar Rav Papa heichi nedayeinu lei lehai dina. How
should the judges deal with this case? נימלא לדידיה זיל שלים. Neimali
ledidei zil shalim.
So what should we say- so to the guy who was the
שומר shomer pay the owner. אמר אנא אמרי ליה מהאי רמי. Amar
ana amari lei meihai rami. I told my attendant to do the
right thing, take it from pile A and he took it from
pile B. Okay, נימלא לסרסיה זיל שלים. Neimali lesarsayeih zil shalim. Tell
the attendant pay you took it from the wrong pile. אמר לא
אמר לי מהאי רמי מהאי רמי. Amar lo amar li meihai rami
meihai rami. He didn't say only take it from this one, don't
take it from that one. Now, you could have said okay you
know what if that's reasonable like if the reasonable thing is that
when you say take from this pile you know people if you
don't spell it out for them they'll assume it doesn't make a
big difference, then presumably the responsibility would be on the שומר, shomer,
right? He needed to be more explicit. Again, like I- you know
I don't understand why this is so difficult, like just understand if
it's a reasonable alternative- interpretation the guy would have given that it's
not מקפיד, makpid, then the responsibility lies with the שומר. shomer. If
you should assume that people are supposed to do my exact instructions
with no variation, then the responsibility lies on the- guy who took
it from the wrong pile.
What difference did it make it was the other pile?
They weren't both owned by the same guy? Right, one I owned
and the other I was watching. And I told my guy- I-
I owned pile A, I was watching pile B. I told my
guy take from pile A. So I did what I needed to
do. He assumed what does it make pile A or pile B?
So he took it from pile B. He didn't tell me not
to take from pile B. So again, to me the question would
simply be what's the reasonable expectation if there was a reason to
think that the guy would understand that I wasn't מקפיד, makpid, then
it was my responsibility to have been clearer. Anyway, let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says. Okay.
אמר... Amar... Okay. ואי דשהא שהיי ליה לאיתויי ולא אייתי ליה. Ve'i
deshaha shahi lei le'aituyei velo aiti lei. Now, if the pile B
which was- was which I didn't own would have taken more time
to get to and pile A was closer and I'm looking at
my watch and I'm saying to myself you know he should have
been back by now and if he's not back by now the
only explanation is that he went to pile B and not pile
A, so גלי דעתיה דניחא ליה gali da'ateih denicha lei and I
didn't say anything, it showed that I was implicitly okay that he
took from pile B. So that's easy. Okay, בדלא שהא. Bedela shaha.
So that's not the case. They were both next to each other,
I had no way of telling which one he took from. סוף
סוף. Sof sof. The גמרא Gemara says okay so before we figure
out who was negligent, who cares? Who cares who was negligent? סוף
סוף מאי פסידא איכא. Sof sof mai psida ika. הא קא משתרשי
ליה. Ha ka mishtarshi lei. What loss was there right to you
know I basically got the benefit from the guy's hops. His hops
was put into my thing. I benefited from my hops- let me
just give him back- not like the hops were destroyed. It's like-
right he made a contribution to me by giving him- me- me-
his hops unwittingly, I'll give him hops back right? Why do we
have to care whether I was negligent or not? Let's assume nobody
was negligent. I still got this guy's hops you know undeservedly. So
now I should give him hops back. And this משתרשי ליה mishtarshi
lei means I benefited from him. Okay, so the word also sometimes
like ומשתרשי umishtarshi it's like- it's like it's taken root in my
property, meaning this is an important idea you might remember from בבא
קמא, Bava Kamma, we have the idea about משלם מה שנהנית. meshalem
ma she'nehenit.
If I gain benefit from you, even if I wasn't מזיק mazik
you, even whatever, you know, somehow my animal fell into your field
and it got cushioned by the, by the fruit, or it ate
your fruit, you know, and in ways which could be exempt, if
I have benefit from you, I have to give pay you back
for the benefit I received. Okay? So here, even if there was
no negligence, okay, and I'm not חייב hayav to the owner as
a שומר, shomer, I got his hops and they benefited my beer,
I should have to pay him for, I'd have to pay him
back for it.
So we're looking at hops, so they are all similar.
Well, that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. Okay? אמר
רב סמא בריה דרבא דהוה שיכרא חלא. Amar Rav Sama b'rei deRava
dehavah shikhrakhala. No,
no, no. You didn't benefit from his hops. His hops turned your
beer into, into vinegar. Okay? Now, you can't go ask him to
pay you because that was your own negligence, your own beer. Okay?
But, you can't say, well, at least give me back what I
benefited you because I didn't, you didn't benefit him, right? The owner,
you know, you used his hops, it hurt your beer. Okay, so
he can't ask to pay you back what you benefited from him.
But he still can say, okay, but you were מזיק mazik my
hops, you weren't שומר shomer my hops, pay me for them. So
that's why we have to determine who was negligent or not. Okay?
Because there is no benefit to be repaid. רב אשי אמר בכיסי
ומשלם ליה דמי כיסי. Rav Ashi amar bekisi umashlim le d'mei kisi.
What we're dealing with here is we're dealing with like inferior hops.
So your inferior hops, it made my beer not so good. Okay?
So therefore I could pay you back, you know, so paying you
back, you know, what I benefited somehow is still not the same
as the question of who was negligent or not negligent. So the
גמרא Gemara really never fully decides like who was, you know, whether
there was negligence in this case. The גמרא Gemara might be saying
there is no negligence, but you got benefit pay back if there
is. If there isn't benefit, if it turned your stuff into vinegar
then there is no paying back. But again, I think it's quite
interesting all these cases where the גמרא Gemara basically it's like, well,
you made a reasonable assumption, they made a reasonable assumption, neither of
you were negligent. Like to me it seems if you're the שומר,
shomer, you have the primary responsibility, and unless you're doing everything to
make it clear to the other person what they can and can't
do, you know, the buck stops here, the primary responsibility rests on
your shoulders. But the גמרא Gemara at least imagines cases where somehow
nobody is responsible. Okay, we will pick up tomorrow.
Oh yeah, it's really well coordinated
with the עמוד, Amud, sometimes it works out very nicely.